welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we call hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
Joe you had a question that was similar
about gaming game be if you still want
to ask it just just go off you sure
screams I wrote in the eyes of regular
people who aren't there excuse me in the
eyes of regular people those who are in
positions of strategic leverage yet
heads of industry government education
things like that they seem to be locked
into a sort of game a fundamentalism and
have been for many decades this is the
sort of blue church idea and my question
to you is does the game be proud to what
you know about have any concrete plan
from going secondly from nudging these
people's decisions to actually
transforming their framework because
obviously we've heard individually
upgrading our sovereignty being able to
be more effective agents individually
but I don't know if maybe behind the
scenes there have been talks on how to
scale that up is this at all possible I
mean I'm gonna I mean I'm talking with
the person who gave us the gmae gave me
blue church Jordan all and part of that
is this idea which is the religion
that's not a religion and coming trying
to come up with a post religious faith
because here's the idea this is probably
the mum ways my most radical idea I want
to do what like Augustine did as the
Roman Empire is falling he laid the
foundations not single-handedly and I'm
not saying I'm Augustine so please I'm
just using this as an analogy okay but
what they did is they laid the fact they
laid the cultural cognitive grammar for
an entirely different culture and they
stole the culture bottom-up from the
imperial system now again the imperial
system at some point then clamped down
again but nevertheless we shifted to the
middle that we shifted out of antiquity
we shifted to a different world and so I
want to try and do that I want to try
and create
the systems of meaning the religion
that's not a religion the ecologies of
practices the the communities the
networks of communities all of this it's
already happening we really empower it
both in terms of its grammar give it the
best scientific tools for engineering
the practices and the ecology of
practices I basically want to steal the
culture from the people who have been
abusing us for such a very long time and
I usually don't speak politically you
because I think the political framing
is often a deep misrepresentation of the
issue at least the way in which
political discourse has been as you said
it sort of been ossified and I think
this also I think Dan was pointing out
that too the way it's been ossified in
ways that make choice no longer it's
sort of really relevant so all right
this is my sort of most radical thing I
guess I'm gonna say because I want yeah
I want to help steal the culture away
steal it away and do everything I can
and you know Christianity stoled the
culture away from the elites it's time
now new elites form they always will but
the culture changed and it changed in an
important way and that's what I'm trying
to do right now and that's that's what I
see myself doing with a lot of these
other people that's very noble and you
certainly have a lot of people who
aren't in those positions I mean if
you're amides you've sort of grown up in
the world sort of looks like it's
running backwards so it's hard to even
imagine that it's been that way for
decades prior but this decade certainly
feels like it's going there's going to
be some collision between the sort of
fresh traded emerging game be tights and
the sort of entrenched game a leaders um
the whole point about the the whole
point about the metaphor is we can't we
can't win by playing the game that's
right and so
my way of trying to understand what it
is to not play their game and to shift
over to in a totally different game
shift the culture it's to steal the
culture and the way to do that the way
we right the only thing I can get from
history that's been able to do that our
religion but for reasons that I've
articulated I don't want not personally
I mean in terms of the functionality I
don't think the standard model the axial
age model of religion is going to do
what we need in order to steal the
culture as deeply as we need to steal it